I want to teach you how to look for God
in the lows.
Cuz if you can look for him in the lows,
you can only go so low.
Because one Psalm says, "If I make my
bed in Sheol, you are there.
If I make my bed in hell, you are there.
Where shall I go from your presence?
Where shall I ascend? If I ascend to the
heavens, you are there. If I descend to
hell, you are there. If I say, 'Surely
the darkness will cover thee.' Surely
light will become as night to thee, for
you are there. Your presence is
everywhere." So, I want you to look for
God in the lows. Now, the contrast we
have in Psalm 120, why I thought it
would be so great for us to study
together today,
is because on one hand, this psalmist is
going up.
He's going up to Jerusalem. Jerusalem is
in the mountain region. So, to go to
Jerusalem, you go up every time. A song
of ascent.
He's singing a song of ascent as he's
going up,
but it's also a song of lament,
which is grief.
So, he's on his way headed up to
worship,
but there is something that is weighing
him down as he walks.
Every single person who is here in this
room today,
on your way up to worship,
on your way up to lift your hands and
praise God, on your way over here,
there was something that was weighing
you down. It's surprising you don't have
a flat tire from all the weight that was
in the car with the tension that is in
your family and the tension that is in
your heart and the tension of your faith
and your frustration. And I got this
picture that we all, like the psalmist,
while we are on our way up, we are
weighed down.
And I want to tell you, Graham, and I
want to tell you, my friend, that's
normal.
And learning to live with this, it's the
ascent and the lament,
all in the same song,
all in the same
room,
all on the same road,
all in the same mind.
I could get you to think about something
right now that would make you so happy,
you would start dancing. You would even
forget that you don't know how to dance.
You would forget you don't have any
rhythm, and you would start I saw some
of y'all doing it during hallelujah.
I saw it. It got you so happy. We start
thinking about God and how he deserves
the praise, and so happy. And then I
could mention something else if I really
knew you. If I could really get in your
life for 5 minutes, I could say
something else, and you would be so
heavy, your hands would drop, your head
would drop, your heart would fall out.
Because as I'm on the way up, it doesn't
mean I'm not weighed down.
I never praise God because my situation
is perfect. And to wait for a perfect
situation to praise God, to wait for a
perfect situation to have peace, that's
a setup from the enemy. If you
procrastinate your praise or your peace
until your situation is perfect, you'll
never get the peace. Because I'm on my
way up,
and I'm weighed down.
And it was different in his time,
because listen to some of the things he
was dealing with. Verse two. He said,
"Deliver me, oh Lord, from lying lips."
Back in the Bible times, they had liars.
And you know, we've evolved
as a species, but in those days, there
were rampant lies.
You couldn't even tell what was truth
and what was a lie. You couldn't even
tell if it was their real voice or not,
or if it was really their lips moving.
Or Graham showed me a picture the other
day, or a video, of some lion jumping to
the sky, snatching a baby lion from a
bird of prey. And he's like, "Dad, why
are you crying?" It was like about
praying moms jumping up and grabbing
their young from the from the the from
the talons of the enemy. And he saw a
tear in my eye. He said, "Dad, that's
AI. You are crying at AI. It's not
real." But it was powerful and it was
good, and you should look it up when I'm
done preaching. "I don't even know
what's real anymore," the man said. Cuz
on one hand, watch this. I'm going up.
On one hand, there are good things
happening in my life. On one hand, I'm
kind of excited about this new
relationship. On one hand, I'm kind of
excited about what I sense that God
might be moving around. But on the other
hand, there is something heavy. I'm on
the way up, and I'm weighed down.
And I'm on my way to the house of God,
but there's something waiting for me at
home that I have to deal with.
So, let me illustrate this with a
picture, okay? I thought of how do I
break this down?
Not only for Graham's Bible study, who's
wondering, "How do I stay in the youth
camp energy year round?"
But you know, kind of all of us wish we
could live in that youth camp energy all
year round.
Or at the very least, at the Sunday
morning energy year round.
If we would all be as nice to each other
in our vehicles as we are in this
church, what would it be like?
It doesn't take much to get you acting
like you are not a Christian, does it?
All I got to do is put you in four doors
with some glass and aluminum, and you
forget all about the presence. The Lord
is everywhere except your car.
And in that space, all is forgiven.
Um
I thought about it like this. I thought
about the song we were singing earlier.
We've got this song that says, "I call
God on the mountain.
I call God in the valley.
I call God on the good days."
Don't forget those.
Sometimes the moments of our victory
make us more vulnerable than the moments
of our defeat.
Cuz sometimes in the moment of defeat,
you're dependent on God.
But sometimes in the moments of your
victory, you pretend like he wasn't the
one who gave it to you.
So, it's it's a great song. Are y'all
enjoying singing it? I call God on the
mountain. I call God in the valley. And
then we name everything where you could
call God, cuz you could call him
anywhere. You could put anything in
there with two syllables.
It'll sing good. I call God in the
kitchen.
I call God in the bathroom.
You can't say that. Yes, you can say
that. The Lord can go where he wants to,
and he can do what he want. He gave me a
lot of sermons in the bathroom. I call
God everywhere. I call God in the
shower.
Some of us, that's the only place we
sound good singing, so we might as well
call him in there, right? But here's
what I wanted to show you.
I wanted to show you that the mountain
and the valleys look like this. And if
you ever go, just put the first graphic,
please.
That that if you go into a hospital,
and they check your heartbeat,
and it looks like that,
the good news is you're not going to be
in the hospital very long.
You going somewhere else.
But that's a EKG. This is the one I
wanted them to put up first, cuz this is
normal. This is a normal heartbeat. I am
going to say as little about this as
possible, because there are nurses and
doctors that go to my church, and I
don't want you to judge me.
Um
Basically, it's telling me about the
heartbeat and this EKG, and those waves
that you see, those peaks and those
valleys,
that's what life looks like.
Yeah.
Y'all see point R?
I call God on the mountain.
But do you see
point S?
I call God in the
Come on, be the choir, y'all.
And both of them are necessary
for life to be present.
The ascent
and the lament.
I had one just the other day, man. You
know how it happens. You're feeling so
good, and you're feeling so much God,
and it takes one text message. One. This
is how strong my faith is. One text
message, and I can go from trusting
Okay. Okay, I'mma come back behind the
pulpit. I can go from everything is so
wonderful, and I love my neighbor, and I
love you, Jesus. In fact, I think I was
singing and working on a worship lyric
when the text came through. And as I'm
looking for the lyric, here comes a
text, a mean text, a nasty text, an
unnecessary text, and all of a sudden, I
felt the bottom drop out, just like
that. And I'm like, "Where did YOU GO,
GOD?"
FOR THE NEXT HOUR, IT GOT IN MY HEAD.
Has this ever happened to you? Y'all are
looking at me so confused.
Just so quick, just so so offended I was
so offended that I just I was having
this moment with God, and then boom,
dropped down. I went Put it back up
there real quick, y'all. I went from R
to S, just like that.
You ever gone from R to S, just like
that?
I used to think God R
and the devil was S.
But I found out
that in between the prayer
and the answer
is faith.
And faith is the substance of things
hoped for and the evidence of things not
seen. You don't see your heart beating.
That's what the readout is showing you,
that you're still here. Your heart is
beating while I'm talking and you're
still here. There are peaks and valleys
in your life while you are journeying
and sojourning through this pilgrim
experience of being a human, being a
person and you keep thinking it's not
normal and you keep thinking that you're
broken cuz you think that Christianity
is always riding the high. But the
moment that you learn that the God who
is the God of this is the God of that.
And this is what life looks like. It
looks like I'm headed up in one area and
I'm way down in another and I'm headed
up in one area and I'm way down in
another and I got one foot up and I got
one foot down and I'm doing better with
my health but I'm doing worse in my mind
and I'm doing better with my money but
I'm doing worse with my time. And here I
am thinking that there's something wrong
with me when God wanted me to know that
both steps are ordered by the Lord. The
one here, the one there. They are both
ordered by the Lord. Bring me my
teaching screen.
I got to teach you about this
because the enemy wants you to think
that God is here
but not here.
But without here, here does not happen.
[Applause]
So, this message is designed to help you
with your mind today because you keep
thinking what's wrong with me that it
keeps dropping out. What's wrong with me
that I keep having to fight for this.
What's wrong with me that I keep having
to relearn the same lessons. The
transformation and renewal of your mind
is not a one-time event. You have to
walk this out.
You have to walk this out.
You have to walk this out one moment at
a time.
Cuz another thing I found out, put the
chart back up.
Yeah.
Is that not only
are both of those
important
for my heart to be. Not only are both of
those important
for me to know God as my shepherd in the
valley
so I can praise him as my provider on
the mountain.
But all of those things are happening
at the same time.
We used to talk about seasons of
blessing and seasons of burdens, right?
Like praise God on the mountain and call
God on the mountain and then when God's
blessing you in season
and then when you're in the valley
season. If I went around the room today
and asked, are you in a mountain season
or a valley season? The only answer that
would be appropriate is yes.
So, let's try it, class. Are you in a
mountain season or a valley season?
You mean you can go from the valley to
the mountain in a moment?
With a text?
With a thought?
Because
there is something to be said for
seasons where God answers your prayers
and you're looking at it.
There's something to be said for seasons
when you see no proof that he heard your
prayer
and you're going by faith, not sight.
But what I realized looking at that
heartbeat
is that those events
are not months apart.
Those are
moments
apart.
See, I thought God would bless you real
good for about a month and you'll be on
the mountain for a month.
But God doesn't bless you a month at a
time.
He blesses you a moment at a time.
And it is not only the seasons
that we need to celebrate and not only
the seasons that we need to be
strategic. The Lord said to tell you,
think seconds, not seasons.
[Music]
Seconds, not seasons.
Seconds. As a matter of fact, this chart
that is on the screen right now, this
chart is showing you what happens not in
one second in your heart
but in a millisecond.
I had to study that.
I I know some certain things. I know
that a uh a season is made up of about 3
months.
I know that a month is made up of about
4 weeks. I know that a week is made up
of about 7 days. I know that a day is
made up of well, not about 7 days,
exactly 7 days. Let us be clear about
it. And those days are made up of 24
hours and an hour is made up of 60
minutes and a minute is made up of 60
seconds. But to get to a millisecond, I
had to find out that is 1 1,000th of a
second that makes up a minute that makes
up a hour that makes up a day that makes
up a week that makes up a month that
makes up a season. And you keep trying
to handle things a season at a time when
God says
I am the God who beats inside of your
heart. Not every second. Take that
second AND SLICE IT DOWN TO A THOUSAND
AND I am in every millisecond. SO, THE
REASON I PRAISE HIM isn't because I'M ON
THE MOUNTAIN NONSTOP BUT IT'S THAT GOD
CAN DO A MIRACLE IN A MILLISECOND. YEAH,
I SAID IT. I GOT A MILLISECOND MIRACLE
WORKING, way making, company keeping,
never leaving, never forsaking God.
Give your neighbor five high fives and
tell them he can do it in a millisecond.
[Music]
Doesn't this MAKE SENSE TO US?
DON'T WE KNOW NOW WHAT WOW, I COULD GO
FROM THE MOUNTAIN UP HERE TO THE VALLEY
AND AND FOR EVERYBODY WHO SURPRISED US,
I bless the Lord at all times. His
praise shall continually be on my mouth.
Okay, Moses, when you come off the
mountain, make sure you cover your face
cuz you're not always shining and I can
interview your family members and find
out more details if I need to. But
please be honest. I'm on the mountain
FOR A MINUTE BUT MOST of us are one
spilled cup of coffee on our khaki
britches away from saying the name of
the Lord in a DIFFERENT WAY CUZ IT IS
NOT
A one-time event.
And if you can go from the mountain to
the valley in a millisecond
I wonder can God bring you from the
valley?
Come on, let's turn this thing around.
LET'S TURN THIS THING AROUND. LET'S
THINK OF THE GOODNESS OF JESUS
and all
that he's done for you
AND COMMAND YOUR SOUL. CRY OUT,
HALLELUJAH!
THANK YOU, GOD
FOR saving me.
Yeah, COME ON, BASEBALL TEAM. PRAISE GOD
WITH ME. I'M GLAD YOU'RE IN THE HOUSE.
YOU HAD TO BE HERE. GOD WANTED YOU TO
GET this word.
[Music]
So, what it is, when you're here, you're
like, oh, that's God.
The psalmist, back to Psalm 120. I am
not going to get to all this all week
unless y'all WOULD LIKE TO STAY UNTIL
ABOUT 3:00 P.M.
[Applause]
[Music]
THAT DID NOT SOUND CONVINCING. I plan on
wrapping up.
He said, verse one, in my distress I
called to the Lord
and he
answered me.
Past tense.
Circle answered, Justin.
How did he do that?
He's not even here
in this room.
But he hears
what I say.
And even though I can't see him
he can do
what I asked him
to do
from a room
where I cannot see him with my eyes. He
said, I called to the Lord and I
couldn't see him
but he answered
me.
Past tense. Well, if he answered you,
then what is verse two all about?
Deliver me, oh Lord, from lying lips,
from a deceitful tongue. Why does he say
in verse one, he answered me and go on
through the next six verses to describe
a problem that is still waiting for him
at home?
I'll tell you next week.
Y'all want it today?
All right.
I'm not like the Lord. I won't make you
wait.
All right.
The The lie is this.
You know, God is with you
but the devil wants you in this loop.
Not
here.
Now,
in the Old Testament the temple was in
Jerusalem, right? We are the temple of
the spirit of God now.
God is not in this room
until you show up.
Yes, he is. He's in the empty room. You
know what I mean.
God does not fill buildings. He fills
people.
But in the Old Testament, construct the
glory of the Lord will fill the temple,
so they had to go to a location to
worship. So, now get the contrast with
me. He's going, "I'm headed here to
worship,
but I'm holding some stuff as I do,
and I'm in between
I'm in between a battle and a blessing
all in one heartbeat.
You keep thinking the season's going to
change and it's going to be all
mountains. I hope not, cuz then you're
dead.
Then your faith will flatline.
And God's going to give you some of
these, and he's going to give you some
of these, and you will have to learn to
praise him and worship him in the same
heartbeat that your heart is broken.
And praise him and call him holy anyway.
And the enemy will say, "Not here. You
can't praise him here. Not in this
hospital, not in this prison, not in
this rehab. When you get out, yeah, when
you get out, you can give a testimony."
You can give a testimony right now.
Because he's the master of the
millisecond.
When I put it online, I might call it
the master of the millisecond. He
doesn't just command the times and the
seasons and creation from eternity. Not
only is call and response built into the
cadence of creation, but in this moment,
in this heart, he's showing me gaga gaga
gaga. I'm all of it. Gaga gaga gaga. I
reveal myself in the rhythms of the ups,
the downs, the eves, the flows, the
yeses, the nos, the leavings, the
comings. I'm in all of it. It's all me.
I'm in all of it. And the devil will
say, "Well, God is not in this.
Not here.
Not here."
And when he says not here,
have your confidence like the psalmist
did. Because what's so beautiful about
the psalm
is that he says God answered my prayer,
but he doesn't even see the proof yet.
The answer is in past tense,
but the trouble is in present tense.
But he knows. Watch this. Here's your
new loop.
The devil is telling me God is not here,
but I tell the devil,
he heard.
Hey, thanks for stopping by my YouTube
channel. I hope you were blessed today.
If you were, share this with somebody.
Like and subscribe, and leave me a
comment. Let me know where you're
watching from, what we can pray for you
about. Hope to see you back here again
really soon.
[Music]